In this video, we will be covering the
double
slit experiment. And this is one of the
key
pieces of evidence that confirms that
light
is a wave.
It's a photon and it behaves like a wave.
And basically, what this does is you shine
a
beam of light into the double split.
And it's going to create a pattern on the
wall.
And the pattern looks something like this.
It's
going to be bright lights and it fades
away
eventually. But this is basically proving
that
light behaves like a wave. Because in
order
for these bright lights to happen, the
waves
need to have constructive and destructive
interference.
At constructive points, the waves form the
bands
of light and at destructive interference
points,
it's dark. And we will be going over a
couple
of formulas that you will need to know in
order
to do these types of problems. So first of
all,
what is this experiment? Well, in this
experiment,
a screen is placed behind the slit and a
beam
of light is over here. And it's at a
distance
of usually depicted by L from the double
slit.
And each slit basically acts as a source
of
waves because light is going through them.
And what you observe is based off of
constructive
and destructive interference, like I've
said
before. And the key idea is that the path
difference
is delta r.
And the path difference is basically the
distance
between each slit, the length travelled
by each slit. And whether point P is
bright
or dark really depends on delta r.
This is given by the formula delta r
equals
m lambda. And m is basically like the
order
or the number of the fringe.
So this, it would start at zero, and it
would
go to one, two, three, four, and so on.
Same side for this, one, two, three, four,
and
that would be equal to m. Lambda is just a
wavelength.
Now, for spacing on a screen, we need to
use
the spot angle approximation. So in these
setups,
in a double slit experiment, the angles
are
really, really small. So we can use small
angle
approximations, which basically says that
sine
theta equals tan theta, which is equal to
y
over L. So if we know that d sine of
theta,
let's call this theta, equals m times
lambda,
which is r. So d sine theta equals m times
we would get y equals m lambda L over d.
And that is basically one of the main
formulas
that we would have to know for double slit
experiments.
Now, this basically shows that the larger
the
wavelength is, the fringes are further
apart,
because y is the distance between the
fringes.
So the larger the wavelength, the fringes
are
further apart. The larger the length away
from
the slit, the more wider the fringes are
apart.
And for the fringes to be closer together,
you
would need a greater distance of your
slit.
Now, another formula you can use is
delta-y.
The change, the distance between two of
the
bands is equal to theta L over d.
Because m basically depicts the order, and
y
depends purely on the order. So instead of
using
m, you could use delta-y. And that's
another
formula you would be using for this double
slit
experiment. And that's basically all you
need
to know about double slit experiments.
It proves that light acts as
a wave, because it uses constructive and
destructive
interference to prove that. And it also
can
be calculated, a lot of the values can be
calculated
from the formulae we learned over here,
and
the small angle approximation. And that's
all
for what you need to know about the double
slit.
Thank you!